人々はこれまでずっと
自由を得るために闘ってきました
Throughout history,
mankind has been in a constant struggle
for freedom.
例えば 信教の自由
Men have fought for freedom of religion,
言論の自由 報道の自由
freedom of speech, freedom of the press,
束縛や奴隷状態からの自由です
and freedom from bondage and slavery.
人が何を自由と見るかは
その時の社会情勢や
Man’s perception of freedom
is shaped by his environment,
his personal situation,
置かれている状況や年齢などに
左右されます
and even his age.
While growing up, I remember the boys
in my neighborhood getting together
私は子供の頃よく 夏休みの最後の日に
近所の友達と一緒に野球をしました
on the final day of summer vacation
to enjoy what we called
“our last day of freedom” baseball game.
みんなその日のことを
「最後の自由な日」と呼んでいました
We called it that because school started
the next day.
次の日から学校に行かなければ
ならなかったからです
でも今日は 遊べるかどうか
といった自由ではなく
But this matter of freedom is not a game.
Our view of freedom
私たちの命を左右する自由について
考えたいと思います
is a matter of life and death.
自由についてどんな考えや
願いを持っているとしても
No matter what our personal feelings
or needs are regarding freedom,
大切な1つの点を
覚えておく必要があります
we must recognize one fundamental fact.
自由には大きく分けて
2つの種類しかないということです
Basically, there are
only two kinds of freedom:
true freedom from Jehovah
エホバが与える本当の自由と
and false freedom
サタンとサタンの支配する世界が与える
見せ掛けの自由です
that is offered by Satan and his world.
Every person must make a choice
全ての人はどちらかの自由を
選ばなければなりません
between these two freedoms.
Let’s consider what each
of these freedoms represents
それぞれの自由がどんなものか
また私たちの選択が永遠の命の見込みに
and how our choice affects our prospect
どんな影響を与えるかを考えましょう
for eternal life.
Please open your Bibles to Matthew chapter 7.
ご一緒にマタイ 7章を開いて
We’re going to read verses 13 and 14.
13, 14節を読んでみましょう
ここにはイエスが山上の垂訓で
話した例えが出てきます
And here we read an illustration
that Jesus gave in the Sermon on the Mount,
イエスは2つの門と
2つの道について話しました
and in the illustration he speaks
about two gates and two roads.
この2つは いま考えている
2種類の自由とも関係があります
And this also relates
to the two freedoms
that we’re discussing this morning.
Matthew 7:13, 14
マタイ 7:13, 14
—he said:
“Go in through the narrow gate,
「狭い門を通って入りなさい
“because broad is the gate and spacious
滅びに至る門は広くて
その道は広々としており
“is the road leading off into destruction,
それを通って入っていく人は
多いからです
“and many are going in through it;
“whereas narrow is the gate and cramped
一方 命に至る門は狭くて
その道は狭められており
“the road leading off into life,
and few are finding it.”
それを見つける人は少ないのです」
一見 「広々とし」た道の方が
At first glance, this “spacious” road
本当の自由につながる道に
見えるかもしれません
may appear to be the road to true freedom.
Why?
なぜですか
Because it’s easy to travel.
歩きやすいからです
Travelers on this road
can go where they please,
この道を歩く人は 好きな所に行き
好きなように考え
生きることができます
think as they please,
and live as they please.
There aren’t any restrictions
何の制約もなく
ルールも責任もありません
—no rules, no commitments.
実際多くの人は 「自由」というのは
And it’s not surprising
when we realize
that one definition of “freedom”
「誰にも何にも邪魔されずに
is “the ability or capacity to act
without undue hindrance
自分の好きなことを行えることだ」
と考えています
or restraint.”
But this is the freedom
でもこれは サタンとサタンの支配する
世界が与える自由です
that Satan and his world have to offer.
But is it real freedom?
これは本当の自由ですか
Please open to Ephesians chapter 2.
エフェソス 2章を開いて
We’re going to read verses 2 and 3.
2, 3節を読んでみましょう
This scripture describes
the situation of people
この聖句には広い門を入って
who choose to enter that broad gate
広々とした道を歩くことを選ぶ人たちの
状況が書かれています
and then walk the spacious road.
Ephesians 2:2, 3
エフェソス 2:2, 3には
こうあります
describes them this way:
“In which you at one time walked according
「皆さんは以前 今の世の体制に
従って歩んでいました
“to the system of things of this world,
人々に影響を及ぼしている空気の
支配者に従って歩んでいたのです
“according to the ruler
of the authority of the air,
“the spirit that is
その空気つまり精神は
不従順な人たちに行き渡っています
“now at work in the sons of disobedience.
“Yes, among them we all at one time
私たちは皆 以前は
そのような人たちの中で
“conducted ourselves in harmony
with the desires of our flesh,
罪深い欲望に従って生活していました
“carrying out the will of the flesh
自分の意志や考えのままに行動し
“and of our thoughts,
and we were naturally children of wrath
ほかの人たちと同じように
生まれた時から
神の憤りを招く人間でした」
just as the rest.”
気付きましたか この道を
歩んでいる人たちは
Did you notice that the ones
walking on this road
全く自由ではありません
are not free at all?
They have a ruler,
「人々に影響を及ぼしている
空気の支配者」がいます
“the ruler of the authority of the air,”
Satan the Devil.
悪魔サタンのことです
And they also have a master.
主人もいます
They carry out the will of the flesh;
自分の意志のままに行動し
罪深い欲望の奴隷になっているのです
they are slaves of the flesh and its desires.
Please turn to 2 Peter chapter 2,
ペテロ第二 2章を見てみましょう
19節を読みます
and we’ll read verse 19.
These words confirm
この聖句を読むと
サタンの約束する自由が
that Satan’s promise of freedom
見せ掛けのものであることが分かります
is a false promise that results in slavery.
結局は奴隷になってしまうのです
Second Peter 2:19 says:
ペテロ第二 2:19にはこうあります
“While they are promising them freedom,
「自由になれると約束しながら
“they themselves are slaves of corruption;
自分自身が腐敗の奴隷になっています
“for if anyone is
誰かに打ち負かされる人は
overcome by someone, he is his slave.”
その人の奴隷になるからです」
Satan’s road is not the road of true freedom.
サタンの道を歩む人は
本当の自由を得られません
Also, it’s not a freeway.
しかも この道は無料ではありません
In fact, it’s a toll road,
有料道路です
この道を通る人は 非常に高い料金を
支払わなければなりません
and the toll to walk on this road
is very heavy.
This permissive, broad road takes its toll
この広い道を通る人には
代償が求められます
in sexually transmitted diseases,
性感染症になり 家庭が崩壊し
broken homes, bodies and minds
薬物やアルコールの乱用によって
身も心も病んでしまいます
that are sick with drug and alcohol abuse,
暴力によっても
痛めつけられます
and acts of violence.
これだけ高い代償を
払わなければならないのに
This toll is way too expensive
just to walk on a dead-end street
この道は行き止まりです
最後には滅びることになるのです
that ends in destruction.
But now, what about the other road
that Jesus talked about?
イエスが話したもう1つの
道についてはどうですか
He said ‘the gate is narrow’
and ‘the road is cramped.’
「門は狭くてその道は
狭められて」います
Why do so few people
choose to walk this road?
その道を歩むことを選ぶ人が
少ないのはなぜですか
Primarily because very few people today
今 神の律法や原則に従って
生きようとする人が
want God’s laws and principles
to govern their lives.
非常に少ないからです
True, this road has boundaries,
この道にはガードレールのような
境界線があって
but those boundaries help
the ones who walk the road
そこを通る人を守ってくれます
to avoid wrongdoing,
間違った行いを避け 悪い欲望と闘い
to fight wrong desires,
to resist peer pressure
周囲からの圧力やあざけられることへの
恐れに負けないよう
and the fear of ridicule that may come
as a result of walking this road.
助けてくれるのです
広い道を通る人は
自分のことばかり考えます
The broad road is centered on self
—self-indulgence, self-awareness,
自分の喜び 自分の在り方
self-fulfillment, and self-interest.
自分の満足 自分の利益です
In contrast,
それとは対照的に
狭い道を通る人は
this narrow road calls for self-control,
自分をコントロールし
自分を二の次にし
self-denial, hard work,
努力を払い 権威を尊重します
and respect for authority.
But this is the road to true freedom.
この道を通る人は
本当の自由を得ることができます
Interestingly, some scriptures
that talk about the freedom
興味深いことに エホバが与える
自由について述べた聖句の中には
that Jehovah gives may appear to be
a little bit confusing.
ちょっと矛盾しているように
思えるものもあります
For example, let’s open
to 1 Peter chapter 2
例えば ペテロ第一 2:16を
見てみましょう
and verse16.
And as we read it, notice
この聖句を読みながら
the contrasting expressions in this scripture
対照的な2つの言葉に注目してください
ペテロ第一 2:16
—1 Peter 2:16.
「自由の民らしくあってください
It says: “Be as free people,
悪い行いを覆い隠すために
自由を用いてはなりません
“using your freedom,
not as a cover for doing wrong,
あくまでも神の奴隷として
自由を用いてください」
but as slaves of God.”
How interesting that we can be free
興味深いことに 奴隷でありながら
and be a slave at the same time!
自由でいられるのです
ほとんどの人は誰かの
For most people, the idea of becoming
a slave to anyone or anything
あるいは何かの奴隷に
なりたいとは思いません
is not appealing.
However, there are positive aspects
でも 奴隷であることには
良い点もあります
to being a slave.
昔の例を考えましょう
Let’s consider an example.
イスラエルでは
負債を抱えた人は
In Israel, a man who fell into debt
自分を奴隷として売ることで
帳消しにしてもらえました
could sell himself as a slave
to pay off his debt,
でもずっと奴隷でいなければ
ならなかったわけではなく
but this wasn’t a permanent arrangement.
He was to be freed after seven years
7年目かヨベルの年に
自由になることができました
or in a Jubilee year, whichever came first.
どちらか早い方にです
While serving as a slave,
奴隷として仕える人は
雇われ人のように見なされました
he was treated like a hired man;
虐待されることはありませんでした
he was protected from abuse.
奴隷は自由になる時
新しい生活を始められるよう
And when he was released,
his master gave him a gift
to help him get back on his feet.
主人から贈り物をもらいました
This was Jehovah’s arrangement,
これは エホバの取り決めでした
so it gives us a glimpse of what it’s like
エホバの奴隷になるということが
どういうことなのか
to be a slave for Jehovah.
理解する助けになります
The life of an Israelite slave
イスラエル人の奴隷の生活は
とても安定していました
could be so secure
that the slave could choose to remain
中には 生涯主人に仕えることを
選ぶ奴隷もいました
with his master for life.
This arrangement is described
この取り決めについては
出エジプト記 21:5, 6に
こう書かれています
at Exodus 21:5, 6, where it says:
“But if the slave should insist and say,
「しかしもし奴隷が 『ご主人や 妻と
子供たちを愛しています
“‘I love my master, my wife, and my sons;
自由になって出ていきたくは
ありません』と
“I do not want to be set free,’
あくまでも言うのであれば
“his master must bring him
before the true God.
主人はその人を真の神の前に連れていく
“Then he will bring him
up against the door or the doorpost,
そして 戸か戸口の柱の前に連れていき
“and his master will pierce his ear
through with an awl,
彼の耳をきりで突き刺す
and he will be his slave for life.”
こうしてその人は生涯
主人の奴隷となる」
We are like that slave.
私たちもそうです
エホバを深く愛し
Our love for Jehovah
エホバが与えてくれる本当の自由に
深く感謝しているので
and our appreciation
for the true freedom he gives
are so strong that we give our lives to him.
エホバに奴隷として仕えます
生涯エホバの奴隷に
なりたいという願いを
We identify ourselves as Jehovah’s slaves,
not by getting our ears pierced,
耳に穴を開けてもらうことではなく
献身とバプテスマによって表します
but by dedication and baptism.
私たちは皆 選択しなければなりません
When it comes to freedom,
we all must make a choice.
Do we take the broad road
of false freedom
広い道を選んで見せ掛けの
自由を得ようとしますか
offered by Satan and his world?
忘れないでください
この道は死に至ります
Remember, it’s literally a dead-end street.
Or do we take the narrow road
of true freedom?
それとも 狭い道を通って
本当の自由を得ますか
That road is defined
この道には 神の正しい基準という
境界線があります
by God’s righteous standards,
and this is the road
that leads to everlasting life.
そして 永遠の命に至る道です
Even now, we’ve been freed
私たちはすでに いろいろなものから
自由にされています
from fear of the future
and the superstitious fear of death.
将来への恐れや
迷信に基づく死への恐れや
We’ve been freed from the pains
that result from a lifestyle
神の基準を無視することによって
生じる痛みからです
that ignores God’s standards.
The freedom that Jehovah provides
エホバは間もなく 私たちが必要とする
全ての自由を与えてくれます
will eventually give the human family
all of the basic freedoms
that honest-hearted people long for today
今 誠実な人たちが望んでいる自由です
恐れからの自由 犯罪からの自由
—freedom from fear, freedom from crime,
飢え 貧困 汚染 病気
戦争からの自由です
freedom from hunger, from poverty,
pollution, sickness, and war.
May we continue to walk on the road
of true freedom ourselves
ではこれからも 本当の自由が得られる
道を歩み続けましょう
and help others to find the true freedom
そして エホバだけが与えてくれる
本当の自由を見つけられるよう
that only Jehovah can give.
人々を助けていきましょう